<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tactics on Ars Atomica</title>
    <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/tags/tactics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tactics on Ars Atomica</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Illion 2017-2020</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 22:03:07 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/tags/tactics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Solutions to last week&#39;s problems</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/20/solutions-pawnitisation-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 22:03:07 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/20/solutions-pawnitisation-problems/</guid>
      <description>This week is just a quick update with the solution to last week&amp;rsquo;s problems. How well did you do?
The first position wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard insofar as calculations go, but relies more on the ability to see the long winning plan. In particular, one needs to realise that the white king must get out of the corner without letting black out. After seeing that and taking care of a few small tactical details, &amp;ldquo;the rest is just technique&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pawnitisation breaking</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/13/pawnitisation-breaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 22:11:28 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/13/pawnitisation-breaking/</guid>
      <description>Last week I discussed the fundamentals of pawnitisation - make your opponent&amp;rsquo;s bishop useless by putting your pawns on the opposite colour. It lets you draw if you&amp;rsquo;re down a bishop, provided all your pawns can&amp;rsquo;t be attacked by the bishop, and there are no passed pawns. Simple.
But of course, chess is rarely that simple. This week we&amp;rsquo;ll be looking at the exceptions - where white can win even when there are no pawn majorities and no targets for the bishop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A knight &amp; bishop mating invasion</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/22/n-b-mating-invasion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 22:33:46 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/22/n-b-mating-invasion/</guid>
      <description>Bishop and knight normally coordinate poorly in chess. They trip around each other awkwardly, the bishop only controlling squares of one colour, while the fickle knight hops between light and dark squares with each move.
Yet in atomic chess, they can combine harmoniously in a particular tactical sequence that crops up now and then. The knight and bishop invade the opponent&amp;rsquo;s camp to catch the king in a forced mate. Despite the specific circumstances needed for this tactic, the sequence felt common enough that I decided to share it with you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New to nuke: Opening queen tactics</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/25/n2n-opening-q-tactics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 20:16:52 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/25/n2n-opening-q-tactics/</guid>
      <description>This series is for players new to atomic. In this installment we look at common queen tactics you will surely come across and learn to watch out for.
The knights may be the fastest pieces out of the gates, but the queen is the real menace, combining deadly mobility with the ability to single-handedly deliver mate. Many of the opening traps in atomic are associated with the queen, threatening multiple mates at once or to sneaking into the enemy&amp;rsquo;s camp along weak diagonals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New to nuke: Opening knight tactics</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/22/n2n-opening-n-tactics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 21:39:16 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/22/n2n-opening-n-tactics/</guid>
      <description>This series is for players new to atomic. In this installment we look at common knight tactics you will surely encounter or use without even trying.
If you&amp;rsquo;ve played atomic a couple times, you&amp;rsquo;d notice that knights can be very dangerous in the opening. It may seem difficult to deal with them jumping into your half of the board and winning material or the game. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore some common knight tactics, and how to defend against them.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
