<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pawns on Ars Atomica</title>
    <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/tags/pawns/</link>
    <description>Recent content in pawns on Ars Atomica</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Illion 2017-2020</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 22:03:07 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/tags/pawns/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Solutions to last week&#39;s problems</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/20/solutions-pawnitisation-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 22:03:07 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/20/solutions-pawnitisation-problems/</guid>
      <description>This week is just a quick update with the solution to last week&amp;rsquo;s problems. How well did you do?
The first position wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard insofar as calculations go, but relies more on the ability to see the long winning plan. In particular, one needs to realise that the white king must get out of the corner without letting black out. After seeing that and taking care of a few small tactical details, &amp;ldquo;the rest is just technique&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pawnitisation breaking</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/13/pawnitisation-breaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 22:11:28 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/13/pawnitisation-breaking/</guid>
      <description>Last week I discussed the fundamentals of pawnitisation - make your opponent&amp;rsquo;s bishop useless by putting your pawns on the opposite colour. It lets you draw if you&amp;rsquo;re down a bishop, provided all your pawns can&amp;rsquo;t be attacked by the bishop, and there are no passed pawns. Simple.
But of course, chess is rarely that simple. This week we&amp;rsquo;ll be looking at the exceptions - where white can win even when there are no pawn majorities and no targets for the bishop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The block and the lune - pawn play made easy</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/26/block-lune/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2017 21:58:40 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/26/block-lune/</guid>
      <description>Pawns have long given me trouble in atomic chess. They don&amp;rsquo;t seem to obey the same rules as their normal chess counterparts: no doubling, controlling space differently, isolation not being a weakness. Worse still, calculating pawn moves and captures in endgames had usually left me completely confused and overlooking moves. The brute force approach to evaluating each pawn move on its own was a straight road to time trouble and blunders, letting opponents escape with draws or even wins.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
