<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ars Atomica</title>
    <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ars Atomica</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Illion 2017-2020</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 21:24:48 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Classic FICS: subtle space</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2019/12/13/classic-fics-subtle-space/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 21:24:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2019/12/13/classic-fics-subtle-space/</guid>
      <description>This time, we&amp;rsquo;re looking at a FICS blitz game from 2008. One of the strongest atomic players, siggemannen, takes the black pieces against luckybbad in a 3 minute, no increment game.
FICS database number: 214032815
View the complete game analysed on lichess.
luckybbad (1934) - siggemannen (2306), 3+0, FICS 2008-11-02 1. e3 e6 2. Qf3 f5 3. Qh5+ g6 4. Qh4
White opts to trade queens early. This particular line might be criticised in some quarters as unambitious.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sente and gote</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2019/08/07/sente-and-gote/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2019 17:19:08 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2019/08/07/sente-and-gote/</guid>
      <description>There is much to learn from the study of chess and chess-like games in Asia. Two useful terms we can borrow from their literature are sente and gote, which relate to the concept of the initiative.
Sente (pronounced sen-teh, 先手) and gote (go-teh, 後手) are terms frequently encountered when studying the Japanese games of go and shogi. I find that they are clearer and more focused terms than &amp;ldquo;the initiative&amp;rdquo; that we have in chess.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2018/07/22/testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 18:47:03 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2018/07/22/testing/</guid>
      <description>Hugo shortcode test (there should be something below this line:)
   (FEN: rnbqkbnr/pppppppp/8/8/8/8/PPPPPPPP/RNBQKBNR w KQkq - 0 1)     (FEN: 6kK/4p1p1/6P1/7B/3P4/8/8/8 w - - 0 1)   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solutions to last week&#39;s problems</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/20/solutions-pawnitisation-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 22:03:07 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/20/solutions-pawnitisation-problems/</guid>
      <description>This week is just a quick update with the solution to last week&amp;rsquo;s problems. How well did you do?
The first position wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard insofar as calculations go, but relies more on the ability to see the long winning plan. In particular, one needs to realise that the white king must get out of the corner without letting black out. After seeing that and taking care of a few small tactical details, &amp;ldquo;the rest is just technique&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pawnitisation breaking</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/13/pawnitisation-breaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 22:11:28 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/13/pawnitisation-breaking/</guid>
      <description>Last week I discussed the fundamentals of pawnitisation - make your opponent&amp;rsquo;s bishop useless by putting your pawns on the opposite colour. It lets you draw if you&amp;rsquo;re down a bishop, provided all your pawns can&amp;rsquo;t be attacked by the bishop, and there are no passed pawns. Simple.
But of course, chess is rarely that simple. This week we&amp;rsquo;ll be looking at the exceptions - where white can win even when there are no pawn majorities and no targets for the bishop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pawnitisation - the bad bishop</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/06/pawnitisation-bad-b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 21:59:27 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/06/pawnitisation-bad-b/</guid>
      <description>Only half the chessboard is ever available to a bishop, the other half forever off-limits. The poor bishop vacillates between its allowed squares, while the enemy pieces taunt it, safely out of reach on the opposite-coloured squares. It is free, unopposed, but with no purpose or function.
When you&amp;rsquo;re up just a bishop that has literally nothing to attack, its existence is almost irrelevant to the position.
What is &amp;ldquo;pawnitisation&amp;rdquo;? Pawnitisation is an endgame defence against such a bad bishop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One player&#39;s thoughts on the opening</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/29/one-player-thoughts-opening/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 21:22:24 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/29/one-player-thoughts-opening/</guid>
      <description>This is a little ramble about openings and how I regard this phase of the game. It probably reads more like an opinion piece than anything, but I did try to include a couple nuggets of knowledge here and there.
What are openings? When one thinks of openings, one would maybe think of long lines and move orders. I instead like to think of openings in terms of their associated middlegame patterns and strategies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A knight &amp; bishop mating invasion</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/22/n-b-mating-invasion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 22:33:46 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/22/n-b-mating-invasion/</guid>
      <description>Bishop and knight normally coordinate poorly in chess. They trip around each other awkwardly, the bishop only controlling squares of one colour, while the fickle knight hops between light and dark squares with each move.
Yet in atomic chess, they can combine harmoniously in a particular tactical sequence that crops up now and then. The knight and bishop invade the opponent&amp;rsquo;s camp to catch the king in a forced mate. Despite the specific circumstances needed for this tactic, the sequence felt common enough that I decided to share it with you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New to nuke: Rook invasions</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/15/n2n-r-invasions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 22:21:47 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/15/n2n-r-invasions/</guid>
      <description>This series is for players new to atomic. In this installment we look at how a single rook can be fatally dangerous, and a simple principle to help evaluate the situation.
Only the queen can by herself mate the enemy king. But a rook in the middlegame can be equally devastating if the enemy king is surrounded by his own forces. Once a rook slips into the enemy position unchecked, it usually guarantees at least a perpetual, if not an outright win.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mined squares - seeing danger</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/08/mined-squares-danger/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 22:33:42 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/08/mined-squares-danger/</guid>
      <description>In order to play any kind of chess well, board vision is required. Put simply, it&amp;rsquo;s the ability to see which squares are under threat and which squares are safe for your pieces. In atomic however, &amp;ldquo;safe&amp;rdquo; doesn&amp;rsquo;t just mean &amp;ldquo;not attacked by your opponent&amp;rdquo;.
Because captures trigger an explosion that affect adjacent squares, you should always be wary of leaving your pieces next to each other, or next to your own pawns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New to nuke: Basic endgames</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/02/n2n-basic-endgames/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 01:11:43 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/02/n2n-basic-endgames/</guid>
      <description>This series is for players new to atomic. In this installment we cover three fundamental endgames one needs to master.
It happens often: one side is up a massive amount of material and is comfortably winning. Yet, when more pieces are traded off, the losing side&amp;rsquo;s king walks right up next to the opponent&amp;rsquo;s king where it&amp;rsquo;s immune to checks. Suddenly the win isn&amp;rsquo;t the clear-cut stomp it appeared to be, the winning side panics and the game ends up drawn after some ineffectual flailing about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The block and the lune - pawn play made easy</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/26/block-lune/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2017 21:58:40 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/26/block-lune/</guid>
      <description>Pawns have long given me trouble in atomic chess. They don&amp;rsquo;t seem to obey the same rules as their normal chess counterparts: no doubling, controlling space differently, isolation not being a weakness. Worse still, calculating pawn moves and captures in endgames had usually left me completely confused and overlooking moves. The brute force approach to evaluating each pawn move on its own was a straight road to time trouble and blunders, letting opponents escape with draws or even wins.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New to nuke: Opening queen tactics</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/25/n2n-opening-q-tactics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 20:16:52 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/25/n2n-opening-q-tactics/</guid>
      <description>This series is for players new to atomic. In this installment we look at common queen tactics you will surely come across and learn to watch out for.
The knights may be the fastest pieces out of the gates, but the queen is the real menace, combining deadly mobility with the ability to single-handedly deliver mate. Many of the opening traps in atomic are associated with the queen, threatening multiple mates at once or to sneaking into the enemy&amp;rsquo;s camp along weak diagonals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New to nuke: Opening knight tactics</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/22/n2n-opening-n-tactics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 21:39:16 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/22/n2n-opening-n-tactics/</guid>
      <description>This series is for players new to atomic. In this installment we look at common knight tactics you will surely encounter or use without even trying.
If you&amp;rsquo;ve played atomic a couple times, you&amp;rsquo;d notice that knights can be very dangerous in the opening. It may seem difficult to deal with them jumping into your half of the board and winning material or the game. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore some common knight tactics, and how to defend against them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New to nuke: First steps</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/21/n2n-first-steps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2017 01:57:14 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/21/n2n-first-steps/</guid>
      <description>This series is for players new to atomic. Later installments will feature material geared towards correcting beginner mistakes and developing a rounded skillset.
This first post in the series is about getting off on the right foot: by playing games. More so than any concrete advice, it&amp;rsquo;s better to jump right into a couple games with a vague idea or two about the variant (see the end of the article) and the intention to have fun.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
