<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>general-advice on Ars Atomica</title>
    <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/tags/general-advice/</link>
    <description>Recent content in general-advice on Ars Atomica</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Illion 2017-2020</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2019 17:19:08 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/tags/general-advice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sente and gote</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2019/08/07/sente-and-gote/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2019 17:19:08 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2019/08/07/sente-and-gote/</guid>
      <description>There is much to learn from the study of chess and chess-like games in Asia. Two useful terms we can borrow from their literature are sente and gote, which relate to the concept of the initiative.
Sente (pronounced sen-teh, 先手) and gote (go-teh, 後手) are terms frequently encountered when studying the Japanese games of go and shogi. I find that they are clearer and more focused terms than &amp;ldquo;the initiative&amp;rdquo; that we have in chess.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One player&#39;s thoughts on the opening</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/29/one-player-thoughts-opening/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 21:22:24 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/29/one-player-thoughts-opening/</guid>
      <description>This is a little ramble about openings and how I regard this phase of the game. It probably reads more like an opinion piece than anything, but I did try to include a couple nuggets of knowledge here and there.
What are openings? When one thinks of openings, one would maybe think of long lines and move orders. I instead like to think of openings in terms of their associated middlegame patterns and strategies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mined squares - seeing danger</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/08/mined-squares-danger/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 22:33:42 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/08/mined-squares-danger/</guid>
      <description>In order to play any kind of chess well, board vision is required. Put simply, it&amp;rsquo;s the ability to see which squares are under threat and which squares are safe for your pieces. In atomic however, &amp;ldquo;safe&amp;rdquo; doesn&amp;rsquo;t just mean &amp;ldquo;not attacked by your opponent&amp;rdquo;.
Because captures trigger an explosion that affect adjacent squares, you should always be wary of leaving your pieces next to each other, or next to your own pawns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New to nuke: First steps</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/21/n2n-first-steps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2017 01:57:14 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/08/21/n2n-first-steps/</guid>
      <description>This series is for players new to atomic. Later installments will feature material geared towards correcting beginner mistakes and developing a rounded skillset.
This first post in the series is about getting off on the right foot: by playing games. More so than any concrete advice, it&amp;rsquo;s better to jump right into a couple games with a vague idea or two about the variant (see the end of the article) and the intention to have fun.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
