<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>endgames on Ars Atomica</title>
    <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/tags/endgames/</link>
    <description>Recent content in endgames on Ars Atomica</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Illion 2017-2020</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 01:25:33 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/tags/endgames/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>アトミックの参考書</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 01:25:33 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/resources/</guid>
      <description>これまで私がアトミックをプレイした経験を元に、私を含めた多くの方々にとってプラスとなるよう、沢山の教材を作ってきた。 これは主にリチェスのスタディの集まりから出来ており、様々な異なるトピックが含まれている。 PGNで提供することを将来検討するかもしれないが、リチェスのスタディが進化し続けると思う（訳者注：「のでリチェスのスタディを見てもらうほうが良いだろう」という意味と思われる）。
エンドゲーム アトミックで学ぶべきことの中でも、おそらくエンドゲームが最も重要なトピックだ。これは初心者であれ上級者であれ当てはまることだ。 基本テクニックは普通のチェス（訳注：以下単にチェスと呼ぶ）のエンドゲームと大きく異なる。 以下に示した最初の３つのスタディが、あらゆるアトミックのエンドゲームテクニックの中でたぶん実戦において最も重要だろう。
訳注：以下では、ピースをアルファベット1文字で略すことがある。
 K：キング Q：クイーン R：ルーク B：ビショップ N：ナイト P：ポーン   孤立キングのエンドゲーム - 孤立キングとの戦いにおける勝ち方を示した。KQ, KQQ, KQB, KRR, KRB, KRN対孤立Kのパターンを網羅している。   KQP対KP - クイーンを1つ得した状態からの勝ち方を示した。最も重要な”勝てる局面を勝ちきる方法”であり、習得するべきだ。このエンドゲームは、なぜ1ポーンのマテリアル差（訳注：駒の損得）がアトミックで勝利に繋がるのかを示している。   KQ対KP - これもまた重要なエンドゲームの一つであり、基礎的なエンドゲームの中では最もトリッキーなものでもある。トップ10に入るほどのプレイヤーであっても、（クイーン対ルークポーンの局面で）間違えたことがある。このエンドゲームは、マテリアルで互角な状態のポーン昇格レースが決着した後に生じる。局面によっては、ポーンを持っている側がドローを取れることさえある。  下に示した残りのスタディは、上の3つと同じぐらい最重要ということはないだろう。だがこれらのスタディを知ることで、局面を勝てるエンドゲームに持ち込む必須の武器を手に入れることになる。つまりどうやって勝てるエンドゲームに持ち込むか考える時に、間接的にミドルゲーム（中盤）の指し手が正確になる。
 ポーン化 - &amp;ldquo;ポーン化&amp;quot;という考え方を示す。片方のプレイヤーがポーンだけしか持っておらず、もう片方のプレイヤーがポーンとビショップを持っている場合を考える。ビショップを持っている側は、相手ポーンが全てビショップと違う色のマスにいれば、ビショップの使い道は無いと悟るはずだ。このようなエンディングでは、ポーンストラクチャーやツークツワンクに絡んで、非常にトリッキーな考え方が通用する場合がある。ポーン化の考え方を知っていれば、本来負けるはずだった多くの対局をドローにすることもできるし、ドローになるはずだった対局を勝ちにすることもできる。   三角形ルール - KP対Kのエンドゲームをもっと簡単に読み切るための方法として、三角形ルールが提唱されている。これはチェスにおける正方形ルールに似ている。ここで示した考え方は、ある種のもっと複雑なエンドゲームを解析するのに役立つ。   KPP対KP: バックワードポーン - ポーン2つ対ポーン1つの局面では、先にポーンを昇格させた側が勝利を得る。 だがポーン1つの側が、ポーンで相手のポーン2つをせき止めている場合は、KQ対Kのパターンに持ち込まれる可能性があり、この場合連結キングにする以外にドローにする方法はない。それでも、いくつかトリッキーな勝ち方が存在しているし、相手が受け方を間違えるという希望もある（受け間違えるのは驚くほど簡単だ）。正しい受けのテクニックを学ぼう。受けのテクニックを学ぶのはこれが最後でいい。一度学べば、今後二度と0.5点を落とす心配をしなくてよくなる。   KPP v KP: exercises - A set of 31 exercises to accompany the above KPP v KP study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solutions to last week&#39;s problems</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/20/solutions-pawnitisation-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 22:03:07 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/20/solutions-pawnitisation-problems/</guid>
      <description>This week is just a quick update with the solution to last week&amp;rsquo;s problems. How well did you do?
The first position wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard insofar as calculations go, but relies more on the ability to see the long winning plan. In particular, one needs to realise that the white king must get out of the corner without letting black out. After seeing that and taking care of a few small tactical details, &amp;ldquo;the rest is just technique&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pawnitisation breaking</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/13/pawnitisation-breaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 22:11:28 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/13/pawnitisation-breaking/</guid>
      <description>Last week I discussed the fundamentals of pawnitisation - make your opponent&amp;rsquo;s bishop useless by putting your pawns on the opposite colour. It lets you draw if you&amp;rsquo;re down a bishop, provided all your pawns can&amp;rsquo;t be attacked by the bishop, and there are no passed pawns. Simple.
But of course, chess is rarely that simple. This week we&amp;rsquo;ll be looking at the exceptions - where white can win even when there are no pawn majorities and no targets for the bishop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pawnitisation - the bad bishop</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/06/pawnitisation-bad-b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 21:59:27 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/10/06/pawnitisation-bad-b/</guid>
      <description>Only half the chessboard is ever available to a bishop, the other half forever off-limits. The poor bishop vacillates between its allowed squares, while the enemy pieces taunt it, safely out of reach on the opposite-coloured squares. It is free, unopposed, but with no purpose or function.
When you&amp;rsquo;re up just a bishop that has literally nothing to attack, its existence is almost irrelevant to the position.
What is &amp;ldquo;pawnitisation&amp;rdquo;? Pawnitisation is an endgame defence against such a bad bishop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New to nuke: Basic endgames</title>
      <link>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/02/n2n-basic-endgames/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 01:11:43 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://illion-atomic.netlify.app/2017/09/02/n2n-basic-endgames/</guid>
      <description>This series is for players new to atomic. In this installment we cover three fundamental endgames one needs to master.
It happens often: one side is up a massive amount of material and is comfortably winning. Yet, when more pieces are traded off, the losing side&amp;rsquo;s king walks right up next to the opponent&amp;rsquo;s king where it&amp;rsquo;s immune to checks. Suddenly the win isn&amp;rsquo;t the clear-cut stomp it appeared to be, the winning side panics and the game ends up drawn after some ineffectual flailing about.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
